Guide to the US Civil War Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
U.S. Civil War Papers,
ca. 1850-1917
4 linear ft. (ca. 2,000 items in 9 boxes; 1 oversize box; and 1 bound volume)
Columbia University, Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY, 10027.
4079618
History
Scope and Content
Materials relating to the American Civil War and the men who fought in it, chiefly of the Union Army.
Correspondence, manuscripts, documents, photographs, memorabilia, and printed materials. In most instances the letters are addressed to some close relative and record the daily happenings of life on the battle line, in camp or in prison. There are eleven letters from Union War veterans who lost their right arm during the war in response to an award offered by William Oland Bourne, 1819-1901, editor of "Soldier's Friend, a monthly periodical," for the best specimen of left-handed penmanship. There are eleven letters from Capt. O. Baker, Jr. about the difficulties in freighting his ship during the 1863 draft riot in New York. There are a few reports and other official documents, military passes, photographs and a collection of print copies of unusual photographs of military offic
Arrangement
Selected materials cataloged; remainder arranged.
Subjects
United States.--Army--Military life.; Beauregard, G. T. (Gustave Toutant), 1818-1893.; Bourne, Wm. Oland (William Oland), 1819-1901.; Brady, Mathew B., 1823 (ca.)-1896.; Dalzell, James McCormick, 1838-1924.; Dresser, Paul, 1858-1906.; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885.; Rhodes, Elisha Hunt, 1842-1917.; Welles, Gideon, 1802-1878.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; African Americans--History.; Draft Riot, New York, N.Y., 1863.; Penmanship, Left-handed.; Disabled veterans--Rehabilitation.; Albums.; Biographies.; Caricatures.; Diaries.; Maps.; Memorabilia.; Military passes.; Muster rolls.; Photographs.; Poems.; Songs.; Editors.; Merchant mariners.; Soldiers.; Supercargos.; Veterans.; Soldier's Friend.
Access Restrictions
This collection is housed on-site.
Acquisition
Papers Various Purchase and gift
12/21/1992 M-92-12-21 G.E. Brown diary Ethical Culture-Fieldston School Archives Gift
05/02/1995 M-95-05-02 Poem by Dalzell & song by Dresser 2293B Purchase
05/09/1995 M-95-05-09 13 a.l.s. from O. Baker, Jr. 6758B (Friends) Purchase
Gift of Mrs John F. Evans, 1955.
Gift of William Bridgewater, 1965.
Gift of Marjorie Hone, 1967.
Gift of Allan Nevins, 1970.
Gift of Mae Schaettle, 1970.
Gift of Mrs Eldon T. Freed, 1973.
Gift of H.L. Fellows.
Gift of Harvey V. Fondiller, 1983.
Gift of Ethical Culture-Fieldston School Archives, 1992.
- Series I: Correspondence and Manuscripts, Catalogued
  - Adams Family (Box 1)
  - Adams, Charles (6) (Box 1)
  - Adams, Frank G. (179) (Box 1)
  - Adams, George W. (300) (Box 2)
  - Adams, John (5) (Box 2)
  - Adams, Seth (2) (Box 2)
  - Andrus, Clark N. (3) (Box 2)
  - Ash, Nancy (l) (Box 2)
  - Avriett, Martha (1) (Box 2)
  - Badollet, Vigo (1) (Box 3)
  - Balch, H.H. (1) (Box 3)
  - Baker, O., Jr. (Box 3)
  - Barchi, C.A. (1) (Box 3)
  - Barnes, George C. (6) (Box 3)
  - Battey, James L. (16) (Box 3)
  - Beardon, Eliphus (1) (Box 3)
  - Beauregard, G.T. (1) (Box 3)
  - Beckwith, Capt. W.W. (7) (Box 3)
  - Berry, Henry (2) (Box 3)
  - Boggs, A. M, (1) (Box 3)
  - Bond, Hiram Gilbert (1) (Box 3)
  - Borough, H.C. (l) (Box 3)
  - Bourne, William Oland (11) (Box 3)
  - Boyd (?), W.H.P. (1) (Box 3)
  - Brewster, James (4) (Box 3)
  - Britten, Joseph W. (1) (Box 3)
  - Brown, George Edgar (Box 3)
  - Butte, L. P. (1) (Box 3)
  - Chapman, W. (1) (Box 3)
  - Coan, Lt. (?) (1) (Box 3)
  - Coleman, R. L. (1) (Box 3)
  - Cook, Willard (2) (Box 3)
  - Coomes, James M. (3) (Box 3)
  - Creasman, Nancy (1) (Box 3)
  - Crothers, Samuel D. (1) (Box 3)
  - Crowley, J. D. (1) (Box 3)
  - Daily, S. (1) (Box 3)
  - Davis, John H. (8) (Box 3)
  - Dominguez, Vincente J. (1) (Box 3)
  - Drown, Joshua (13) (Box 3)
  - Eames, Albert (7) (Box 3)
  - Ewing, W.L. & Co. (1) (Box 3)
  - Fauntleroy, Mrs. J. (1) (Box 3)
  - Flagg, Albert (7) (Box 3)
  - Flagg, Charles B. (49) (Box 3)
  - Foster, Abiel (1) (Box 3)
  - Gardner, William (l) (Box 3)
  - Gilman, John E. (1) (Box 3)
  - Greene, Dana (l) (Box 3)
  - Heaton, Jacob (l) (Box 3)
  - Hendrick, James (1) (Box 3)
  - Henries, H. C. (l) (Box 3)
  - Hidden, Emily P. (3) (Box 3)
  - Holmes, Alexander (2) (Box 3)
  - Huntley, Ambrode A. (98) (Box 3)
  - Hulse, Daniel (228) (Box 4)
  - Jarvis, T. (1) (Box 4)
  - Johnson, Adelbert (21) (Box 5)
  - Johnston, R.M.I.C. (1) (Box 5)
  - Jones, I. E. (1) (Box 5)
  - Jordan, M. A. (l) (Box 5)
  - Joynes, Edward T. (l) (Box 5)
  - Kelley, E. M. (57) (Box 5)
  - Kendall, E.M. (27) (Box 5)
  - Kent, Evarts B. (l) (Box 5)
  - Knapp, Arthur M. (l) (Box 5)
  - Ladd, George W. (10) (Box 5)
  - Lafever, Augustus (4) (Box 5)
  - Lake, Israel (l4) (Box 5)
  - Lawrence, John Tharp (1) (Box 5)
  - Little, J. H. (1) (Box 5)
  - Lovejoy, Benjamin G. (3) (Box 5)
  - McDonald, John (23) (Box 5)
  - McEwan, Wm. G. (1) (Box 5)
  - McGill, Thomas (22) (Box 5)
  - Paddock, Mary S. (1) (Box 6)
  - Patrick, Brig. Gen M.P. (2) (Box 6)
  - Perry, John (l) (Box 6)
  - Perry, Raymond (1) (Box 6)
  - Phillips, Dude (l) (Box 6)
  - Pierson, John and Ruth (4) (Box 6)
  - Pierson, Julia Ann Enoch (10) (Box 6)
  - Pierson Family (9) (Box 6)
  - Pitkin, Capt. P.P. (30) (Box 6)
  - Place, Nancy (1) (Box 6)
  - Plummer, Charles H. (2) (Box 6)
  - Prescott, Samuel H. (1) (Box 6)
  - Price, H. G. (l) (Box 6)
  - Ramsey, E. D. (l) (Box 6)
  - Read, Elijah (91) (Box 6)
  - Read, Nathan (52) (Box 6)
  - Rhodes, Gen. Elisha H (16) (Box 6)
  - Ricketts, Frances Ann Lawrence (Mrs. James B.(6) (Box 6)
  - Rivers, N.H. (1) (Box 6)
  - Rodman (Box 6)
  - Samuels, Green B. (1) (Box 6)
  - Shaw, James, Jr. (3) (Box 6)
  - Snyder, Thomas J. (1) (Box 6)
  - Spofford, Florence P. (2) (Box 6)
  - Steinwehr, Adolf von (l) (Box 6)
  - Suratt, A. J. (2) (Box 6)
  - Synch, J. M. (l) (Box 6)
  - Taylor, Seneca W. (h) (Box 6)
  - Thompson, William S. (1) (Box 6)
  - Triminal, T. J. (l) (Box 6)
  - Throop, George H. (Box 6)
  - Tripp, Capt. Robt. C. (l) (Box 6)
  - Tunholm, G. A. (l) (Box 6)
  - Turner, Thomas (22) (Box 6)
  - U.S. Civil War. Autographs (58p.) (Box 6)
  - Vars, N. B. (7) (Box 6)
  - Wallace, Elliot M. (8) (Box 6)
  - Weaver, Caius A. (1) (Box 6)
  - Welles, Gideon (l) (Box 6)
  - White, Cyrus (2) (Box 6)
  - White, Edward D. (3) (Box 6)
  - Whitson, Mrs. G. W. (1) (Box 6)
  - Wilson, Micajah R. (1) (Box 6)
  - Winder, John H. (3) (Box 6)
  - Winter, William (l) (Box 6)
  - ------, Ebenezer (l) (Box 6)
  - ------, George (1) (Box 6)
- Series II: Arranged Material
  - Biographical sketches of two Civil War Soldiers: John Adair McDowell and Francis Markoe Cummins (Box 7)
  - Broadsides and newspapers (Box 7)
  - Confederate loan certificate, 1861 (Box 7)
  - Maps (Box 7)
  - Memorabilia (Box 7)
  - Military orders and reports (Box 7)
  - Military passes, receipts and currency forms (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous documents (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous letters (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous military communications (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous personal letters, 1859-1866 (Box 7)
  - Muster rolls, l86l (Box 7)
  - Arkansas Eastern District. St. Francis River Command (Box 8)
  - Military and civil records, 1860-1866. 3 manuscripts vols.: (Box 8)
    - 1 vol. accounts (Box 8)
    - 2 vols. military records (Box 8)
  - See also a photograph album in Box 9 (Box 8)
  - Photographs (Box 9)
  - Photograph albums – 2 (Box 9)
  - Pictorial envelopes (Box 9)
  - Print copies of photographs of Military Officers - 82 (Box 9)
  - Confederacy in Petticoats, Cartoon of Jefferson Davis (Box 571)
  - Bound volume: Letters received by Isaac Pennypacker, 1899-1902 relating to his biography of General George W. Meade, General Meade, Appleton, 1901. (ca.186 items) The letters are in two categories: (Box 599)
    - 1: Relating to the problems of publishing
    - 2: From relatives, friends, etc., offering comment, correction, or addition to material published in the book. Many of the incidents described in these letters were witnessed by the writers.
- Series III: Correspondence of General Isaac B. Pennypacker of Haddonfield, New Jersey
  - Collection of 186 letters and notes received by Pennypecker, 1899 to 1902 with a few copies of his own for clarity. The total collection concerns Pennypacker"s civil war biography of General George D Meade "General Meade" published by Appleton in 1901 in the "Great Commander Series," under the general editorship of James Grant Wilson. The collection breaks down into to categories: (Box 599)
    - 1. Letters from members of General Mead’s family, veterans of the same Civil War campaigns, and former associates of General Meade These make corrections, comment, clarify incidents or are inclined to argue about Pennypecker’s interpretation of battles and campaigns, especially when they feel that their hero or former regiment has been slighted. Thus here we get first hand unpublished accounts of many controversial Civil War incidents.
    - 2. Letters relative to the problems of publishing the book. Correspondence from members of the firm of Appleton, reviewers, etc., concerning such things as editing, procurement of maps, sales, royalties, advertising, reviews.
  - Prints of photographs by Mathew Brady, c. 186O-1864. Silver prints, 13.5 x 16.5 mounted on board 16" x 20". Each print from the original Brady negative, printed ca. 1950 from negatives which were subsequently donated to the Smithsonian Institution. (Box 682-683)
  - Arthur, Prince, Duke of Connaught (Box 682-683)
  - Bodisco, Mrs. (Box 682-683)
  - Boutwell, George (Box 682-683)
  - Bull Run (Box 682-683)
  - Burying the Dead (Box 682-683)
  - Captain of Gun Boat "Hunchback" (Box 682-683)
  - Cartridge Manufactory (Box 682-683)
  - Catacazy, Madame (Box 682-683)
  - Custer, George, General (Box 682-683)
  - Factory Hospital, Fredericksburg (Box 682-683)
  - Fairfax Station (Box 682-683)
  - Fessenden, William (Box 682-683)
  - First Connecticut Battery (Box 682-683)
  - Fish, Hamilton (Box 682-683)
  - Fourth Massachusetts Battery (Box 682-683)
  - Gage, Mr., and Brother (Box 682-683)
  - Grant, Jesse and Nelly (Box 682-683)
  - Grant, Ulysses S., General, Seated (Box 682-683)
  - Grant, Ulysses S., General, Standing (Box 682-683)
  - Grant, Ulysses S., President (Box 682-683)
  - Hancock, Winfield, General, Seated (Box 682-683)
  - Hancock, Winfield, General, Standing (Box 682-683)
  - Harwood, Miss (Box 682-683)
  - Hoar, Ebenezer (Box 682-683)
  - Hut; Eleventh Rhode Island V. M. (Box 682-683)
  - In the trenches at Fredericksburg (Box 682-683)
  - Lincoln, Abraham, Seated (Box 682-683)
  - Lincoln, Abraham, Standing (Box 682-683)
  - Logan, John Alexander, and Family (Box 682-683)
  - Machine Shops, Alexandria (Box 682-683)
  - Officers' quarters (Box 682-683)
  - Robeson, George (Box 682-683)
  - Shaffer, Mrs. (Box 682-683)
  - Sheridan, Philip, General (Box 682-683)
  - Stanton, Edwin (Box 682-683)
  - Unidentified Child (Box 682-683)
  - Unidentified Lady (Box 682-683)
  - Unidentified Little Girl (Box 682-683)
  - Unidentified Young Woman (Box 682-683)
  - Entries for the identified portraits have been added to the General Portrait Collection file. Gift of Harvey V. Fondiller, 1983 (Box 682-683)